Today's דף daf is נה Nun Hey of... צה, Tzaddi Hey, 95.
נ Nun 90. Anyway, today's דף daf is צה. Tzaddi Hey. We
pick up at the bottom of צד עמוד ב Tzaddi Dalet Amud
Bet and we are dealing with a case about rather than a
woman whose husband is reported dead and then the husband turns up
alive, a husband whose wife is reported dead, marries her sister, and
then the wife turns up alive. The גמרא Gemara dealt with the
issues, some issues according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, if that would
create problems for the husband because would this woman who would this
would the sister require now a גט Get and if the sister
would require a גט, Get, then though then he couldn't go back
to his wife because then it would be like he had been
married to the sister. But we don't say that, we reinterpret רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, so anyway, even according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
presumably he can go back to his first wife. Now the גמרא
Gemara picks up towards the bottom of צד עמוד ב Tzaddi Dalet
Amud Bet the following way. אמר ליה רב אשי לרב כהנא, Amar
lei Rav Ashi le-Rav Kahana, אי רבי עקיבא, Ei Rabbi Akiva, line
starts with the word עקיבא Akiva about 12 lines from the bottom.
אי רבי עקיבא, Ei Rabbi Akiva, if the משנה Mishnah should even
be רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, because the guy doesn't have to give
a גט Get to this sister, so ליתני נמי חמותו. lisni nami
chamosto. Why is the only scenario where an interesting case where a
report of the wife's death would allow him to marry somebody, why
is that only sister? Now for us the answer is because sister
presumably is the only עריות arayot where after the one of the
relevant parties dies she becomes permissible, right? Because it says לצרור לגלות
ערותה עליה בחייה. litzror legalos ervasah aleha bechayeha. So presumably that's the
only scenario that a guy hears his wife dies, it's relevant now
that he can marry someone else, that would be the case of
sister. But one minute, according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva you also
have mother-in-law. Is the הלכה halacha about marrying a woman and her
mother, does it apply even after the wife has died? Is the
man prohibited to marry the mother? So the general assumption is yes,
it applies even after the wife has died, but now we're going
to say maybe according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva it doesn't apply
after the wife has died. So if the משנה Mishnah could be
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, it should have given the case also that
the woman is reported dead, the wife is reported dead, and he
married the mother. So let's take a look. דאמר חמותו לאחר מיתה
בשרפה, De'amar chamosto le'achar misah besreifah, that mother-in-law after the wife dies
is not the case that the תורה Torah says that you burn,
you know that you execute him and her. דתניא, Desanya, it was
taught in a ברייתא. Baraisa. באש ישרפו אתו ואתהן, Ba'eish yisrefu oso
ves-hen, in a fire you shall burn him and them. What does
the פסוק pasuk say? It says a man cannot take a woman
and her mother, כי יקח איש את אשה ואמה, Ki yikach ish
es isha ve'imah, right?
If a man takes a woman and her mother, you shall burn
him and them. So the rabbis ask, what do you mean them?
I mean if he married the woman first and then afterwards he
went ahead and married the mother, what did this poor wife do
that she should be now executed? It was his sin with some
other. So what does this mean? So באש ישרפו אתו ואתהן, Ba'eish
yisrefu oso ves-hen, אתו ואת אחת מהן, oso ves achas meihen, דברי
רבי ישמעאל. divrei Rabbi Yishmael. So רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says it
doesn't mean them, it means one of them. All right, interesting read
of the פסוק. pasuk. So it just means the mother. רבי עקיבא
אומר אתו ואת שתיהן. Rabbi Akiva omer oso ves shteihen. No, both
of them. Now what does that mean? Again, we can't accept that
it literally means the woman, the wife. So there's a debate about
אביי Abaye and רבא Rava how to interpret this debate. בשלמא לאביי,
Bishlama le-Abaye,
according to אביי Abaye this is not a... this is fine because
what does אביי Abaye say? דאמר משמעות דורשין איכא בינייהו, de'amar mashma'us
dorshin ika beina'ihu, that they don't really debate any הלכה, halacha, they
just debate how to read the פסוק. pasuk. דרבי ישמעאל סבר חדא
כתיב ורבי עקיבא סבר תרתי כתיב. De-Rabbi Yishmael savar chada ksiv ve-Rabbi
Akiva savar tartei ksiv. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says it's talking about
one case and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it's talking about two
cases. What does this mean? So it means that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael says like we think, okay, a man married a woman and
her mother, you know you execute him and the mother. רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says it means both of them not in the same
case. It means whether a man married a woman and her mother
or whether he married mother's mother, oh no, that would be a
good guess but no, or whether he married the woman and the
mother's mother, okay? So when it says... when it says כי יקח
איש את אשה ואמה, ki yikach ish es isha ve'imah, it doesn't
mean his first wife and her mother, it means like his wife's
mother and her mother or something like that. You mean he married
three generations? Yeah, something... exactly. So then you burn the mother and
the grandmother, okay? But anyway, nobody really debates... nobody really debates the
הלכה. halacha. Everybody agrees that in all those cases you... both of
them would be, you know, the second and or third woman would
be executed. So then it's not relevant, nobody debates the הלכה, halacha,
nobody says that it makes a difference if the original wife is
alive or not, okay? But אלא לרבא דאמר חמותו לאחר מיתה איכא
בינייהו, ella le-Rava de'amar chamosto le'achar misah ika beina'ihu, but רבא Rava
says there's a real debate and the debate is whether the mother-in-law
is still forbidden after the wife dies, because according to רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva when he reads את שתיהן, es shteihen, it means when
both of them are still alive, that's when the... that's when they
get executed, if the wife was still alive. But if the wife
had died... then it would not be- then you would not execute
him and the mother. Okay, so there's a real- so that's what
the גמרא Gemara is going to say. So what according- but now
we think that it would be permissible. So that's true- ליתניה נמי
כמותיה. lisnye nami kamosay. Why don't we take the case of mother-in-law
in the משנה, Mishnah, another scenario where after hearing that the wife
died, he'd be allowed to marry somebody? So the גמרא Gemara says
no, אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, נהי דמיעטיה קרא משרפה, nehi dimitei kra
misraifah, it's one thing to say that they don't get executed, מאיסורא
מי מיעטיה? me'issura mi mietei? That doesn't mean there's no prohibition. Now
the normal phrase איסורא issura sounds like some weak prohibition, some generic
type of a thing, but you look at תוספות, Tosfos, תוספות Tosfos
says מאיסורא מי מיעטיה רחמנא me'issura mi mietei rachmana to לומר מלאו
וכרת לא מיפטרו lomar melaav vechares lo miptaru אלא משרפה. ella misreifa.
It's not some- it's not some weak prohibition. It's the- it's a
negative prohibition, you get כרת, kares, you just don't get executed. Okay,
but certainly it would not be relevant to include in the משנה.
Mishnah. Yes. Go ahead Dom.
Does this mean that if she- if the daughter continues to live
with him after he marries the
mother?
Yeah, you could have said that, right? That maybe her sin is
that she- that she continues, but somehow the גמרא Gemara assumes- you're
right. I think the reasonable read of the פשט pshat of the
פסוק, pasuk, but the גמרא Gemara assumes no, once that marriage was
okay, the only prohibited marriage was with the mother. Okay. Now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, ותיאסר, vesiaser, now we're going to get
to the heart of the matter, which is is that the fact
that he was- let's give- let's draw the case again, okay? And
this time what- or grandma? All right, all right.
So you've got here ראובן, Reuven, right? He's married to רחל, Rachel,
from yesterday. Okay, right?
We're keeping them from yesterday.
She goes to מדינת הים, medinas hayam, way over here. Okay? And
then he goes ahead and he marries לאה. Leah. Okay? And then
it turns out that his wife is alive. So we say- so,
there's- we say he can go back to רחל. Rachel. Now that
means two things. The first thing it means is we don't look
at this as enough of a marriage. If we looked at this
as a marriage, okay, and then he had to give a גט
get to לאה, Leah, which we suggested yesterday could be according to
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva but we rejected, so if we looked at
it even when she returned as- we would still continue to say
there was some- some semblance of a marriage here, he needs to
give a גט, get, then רחל Rachel would become his wife's, לאה's,
Leah sister, right? אחות גרושתו. achos grushaso. So the first point is
we don't look at this as a semblance of marriage. Very much
in contrast to the woman who married a man when she thought
her husband was dead, we do look at it like a marriage
and she has to get a גט get and live with all
the consequences. Here we don't look at it like a marriage, לאה
Leah doesn't need a גט, get, he can go back to רחל.
Rachel.
It was נישואין. nisuin.
It was נישואין. nisuin. But now the גמרא Gemara is going to
ask, fine, let's not look at it as a marriage. Maybe we
should say the very fact that he slept with לאה Leah should
make רחל Rachel forbidden to him. Now that's a bizarre idea, why
should we ever say such a thing? But it's sort of like
a little bit good for the goose, good for the gander type
of a thing. We say normally a woman, she sleeps with another
man, right? That even if it was
a- not- שוגג shogeg and didn't realize it wasn't her husband, that
makes her forbidden to her husband, right? So here too. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, לא דמיא. lo damya. It's not similar. אשה
דבמזיד אסירה מדאורייתא, Isha debemezid assira mid'Oraisa, this wife that if she
intentionally commits adultery she's forbidden to him biblically, בשוגג גזרו בה רבנן,
bishogeg gazru bah rabanan, when it was unintentional and she slept with
this other man, again ignoring that there was a semblance of marriage,
she slept with this other man, that also makes her forbidden to
her husband. That's the case where the woman's husband is reported dead.
Top of דף צ' עמוד א'. daf tzad amud alef. אחות אשה,
achos isha, but the wife's sister, לאה, Leah, דבמזיד לא אסירה מדאורייתא,
debemezid lo assira mid'Oraisa, that even when he willfully sleeps with לאה,
Leah, his wife רחל Rachel does not become forbidden to him. There's
no דאורייתא d'Oraisa concept that sleeping with the sister makes the wife
forbidden. So בשוגג לא גזרו בה רבנן. bishogeg lo gazru bah rabanan.
So therefore the Rabbis aren't going to say that in this case
where it's unintentional, we're going to make רחל Rachel forbidden.
So basically saying there is no basis for saying A, that he's
quasi-married to לאה, Leah, we dealt with that yesterday, and B, certainly
not- the very sleeping with לאה Leah should make רחל Rachel forbidden.
Let's take a look at that in the גמרא. Gemara.
Yes. Go ahead Dom. Does that mean that there's some category- there's
some category theoretically between נישואין nisuin and זנות? znus?
If it was only זנות, znus, it shouldn't affect רחל. Rachel.
No, the question is maybe if it is זנות, znus, it will
affect her.
Oh, okay, that's what I want to know. So it's the זנות
znus question.
Yep, let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
ותיאסר בשכיבת דאחותה. veseiaser bishchivas de'achosah.
Why not let רחל Rachel be forbidden through sleeping with her sister?
Like when a woman's husband goes to מדינת הים medinas hayam and
she sleeps with another man, that makes her forbidden to her husband.
And again, assuming not because of a semblance of marriage, assuming just
because she slept with another man, so here too. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, לא דמיא. lo damya. It's not similar. אשה דבמזיד
אסירה מדאורייתא. Isha debemezid assira mid'Oraisa. This wife that if she intentionally
commits adultery, she's forbidden to him biblically, בשוגג גזרו בה רבנן. bishogeg
gazru bah rabanan.
When it was unintentional and she slept with this other man, again
ignoring that there was a semblance of marriage, she slept with this
other man, that also makes her forbidden to her husband. That's the
case where the woman's husband is reported dead. Top of דף צ'
עמוד א'. daf tzad amud alef. אחות אשה, achos isha, but the
wife's sister, לאה, Leah, דבמזיד לא אסירה מדאורייתא, debemezid lo assira mid'Oraisa,
that even
when he willfully sleeps with לאה, Leah, his wife רחל Rachel does
not become forbidden to him. There's no דאורייתא d'Oraisa concept that sleeping
with the sister makes the wife forbidden. So בשוגג לא גזרו בה
רבנן. bishogeg lo gazru bah rabanan. So therefore the Rabbis aren't going
to say that in this case where it's unintentional, we're going to
make רחל Rachel forbidden. So basically saying there is no basis for
saying A, that he's quasi-married to לאה, Leah, we dealt with that
yesterday, and B, certainly not- the very sleeping with לאה Leah should
make רחל Rachel forbidden. Let's take a look at that in the
גמרא. Gemara. דתניא, detanya, we learned in a בריתא: braita: אותה—this osa
פסוק pasuk is בשכבה beshichvayah in the case of a woman who
committed adultery. ושכב איש אותה שכבת זרע ve'shachav ish osah shichvas zera
by the פרשה parsha of סוטה, Sotah, ונעלם מעיני אישה ונסתרה והיא
נטמאה ועד אין בה והיא לא נתפסה, v'ne'elam me'einei ishah venistarah vehi
nitma'ah ve'ed ein bah vehi lo nitpasah, right? So it says והיא
נטמאה—she vehi nitma'ah becomes defiled. So from there we see that when
a woman commits adultery, she becomes defiled; she becomes אסורה asura to
her husband. This is where we know this concept that a woman
becomes אסורה asura to her husband when she commits adultery. So here
is the דרשה: drasha: אותה—she, osa when she commits adultery. אותה שכבתה
אוסרתה—her osa shichvasah osartah act of sleeping with another man makes her
forbidden, ואין
שכבת אחותה אוסרתה—but ve'ein shichvas achosah osartah the sex that her sister
has with her husband will not make her forbidden. Okay? So if
a man sleeps with her sister, her husband sleeps with her sister,
that does not make her forbidden. שיכול, sheyachol, okay, so now why
do we need a פסוק? pasuk? I mean, you know, why would
we have thought otherwise? שיכול והלא דין הוא—I sheyachol ve'halo din hu
could have argued otherwise by a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Here is
the קל וחומר: kal vachomer: ומה במקום שבא על איסור קל נאסר
האוסר. uma bemakom sheba al issur kal ne'esar ha'oser. Okay, now it's
a little,
there are all these cryptic terms. I'm going to explain it the
way the גמרא Gemara concludes it. So שבא על איסור קל—when
sheba
al issur kal somebody has sex with an
איסור קל. issur kal. איסור קל issur kal means—for some reason we're
going to call adultery an איסור קל. issur kal. Why is adultery
an איסור קל? issur kal? It's חייב מיתה! chayav misah!
The only reason it's an איסור קל issur kal is in contrast
to a wife's sister, because a married woman could at some stage
become permitted to this man, the adulterer, okay, if she got a
divorce, whereas a wife's sister is always going to be forbidden even
as long as the woman is alive, whereas a married woman could
become permissible if she got a גט. get. So it's a very
tenuous point, okay? The גמרא Gemara is going to go through a
whole discussion and come up to this, which is not a very
satisfying answer, but for now, compared to wife's sister,
a married woman is less of an איסור. issur. Why? Because wife's
sister is always going to be forbidden, even, you know, as long
as the woman is alive, whereas married woman could become permissible if
she got a גט. get. So it's a very tenuous איסור קל.
issur kal. Anyway, the point is like this: if somebody sleeps with—forget
Leah for a minute—some other man here, we'll do our classic Barak
here. Barak, he goes ahead, or you know, we'll have Reuven, but
he's just going to go ahead and sleep with this other woman,
with this other woman, I don't know, Sarah, okay, married to Avraham.
He's not related to her the same, okay. So anyway, okay, we'll
do Dvora and Barak, we'll get back to that. Okay, here's your
Barak and Dvora. Okay, so Reuven goes ahead and he sleeps with
Dvora, okay, while she's married to Barak. He commits adultery, okay. So
he's בעל איסור קל, ba'al issur kal, for now we'll call it
איסור קל. issur kal. What's the consequence? The consequence is that Barak
now is forbidden to his wife,
obviously the adultery and all
that, yeah, no, no, no, well, yeah, well we're not executing anybody,
we're just talking about her being אסורה asura to her husband. Okay?
So בעל איסור קל נאסר האוסר. ba'al issur kal ne'esar ha'oser. Who
is the האוסר? ha'oser? Barak is the האוסר, ha'oser, because of Barak,
that's why Dvora is forbidden. Okay, so he is the האוסר, ha'oser,
he makes her forbidden. So he is the האוסר, ha'oser, okay? So
when he has sex with a wife, the one who defined the
wife's status becomes forbidden to her. Very confusing way of setting it.
נאסר האוסר. ne'esar ha'oser. So ומה במקום שבא על איסור קל נאסר
האוסר, uma bemakom sheba al issur kal ne'esar ha'oser,
מקום שבא על איסור חמור אינו דין שנאסר האוסר?
makom
sheba al issur chamur eino
din shene'esar ha'oser?
Now, if Reuven went ahead and had sex with Leah, which is
being called איסור חמור—just issur chamur accept it, okay—because the wife's sister
for this purpose is seen as more severe, okay, who is the
האוסר? ha'oser? Who makes Leah forbidden?
Rachel. Okay, so he's having sex with איסור חמור, issur chamur, how
much more so should the האוסר, ha'oser, Rachel, become forbidden to him?
That's the logic, okay?
All right, not very persuasive if you ask me. But basically, the
same way sex with a married woman makes her forbidden to the
man who defined her status, sex with the sister should make the
woman who defined her status equally forbidden.
No, no, no, no... No מכל שכן? mikal shekein? No... sister... yeah...
we've left mother. We've left mother.
We don't say that.
We don't. But this is the הוה אמינא. hava amina. This is
the הוה אמינא, hava amina, okay? מקום שבא על איסור חמור אינו
דין שנאסר האוסר. makom sheba al issur chamur eino din shene'esar ha'oser.
That's the הוה אמינא, hava amina, and then we have the פסוק
pasuk that says אותה—that's osa not true, that sleeping with a sister
does not make the woman forbidden. Okay, אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav
Yehuda, says רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, לא נחלקו בית שמאי ובית הלל.
lo necheliku Beis Shammai u'Veis Hillel. Now we're going to find out
there's actually a debate of
בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai about something, possibly.
בית הלל ובית שמאי Beis Hillel u'Veis Shammai did not disagree. unanimous
opinion that if a man has sex with a his wife's mother
that his wife does become forbidden as a result. That sex with
a woman other than his wife will make his wife forbidden to
him.
Okay, and
have to be killed and and forbidden, right, but if there's no
witnesses, mother doesn't get killed. Okay. In that case, the wife does
become forbidden.
במה נחלקו, Bamah nechlaku, by the way, just if you're worried where
this comes from, it comes exactly from the פסוק pasuk we had
a minute ago, which is אותה ואתהן. otah ve-es-hen. Since it says
ואתהן ve-es-hen which פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk includes the wife,
so this דרשה drasha is saying, fine, we might not execute the
wife, but her status is affected when a man sleeps with her
mother. Okay. And when a man sleeps with his wife's mother, his
wife does become forbidden and that we learn out from ואתהן. ve-es-hen.
So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah says that would be a case where
sleeping with the mother would make the wife forbidden and even that
would actually be the unanimous between בית הלל ובית שמאי. Beit Hillel
u-Beit Shammai. במה נחלקו, Bamah nechlaku, there is however debate of בית
הלל ובית שמאי Beit Hillel u-Beit Shammai in the following case. בבועל
אחות אשתו, Bevoel achot ishto, a man has sex with his wife's
sister what we were talking about, שבית שמאי אומרים פוסל, she-Beit Shammai
omrim posel, בית שמאי Beit Shammai actually says actually the sister does
become invalid, it does become אסור asur to him. ובית הלל אומרים
לא פוסל u-Beit Hillel omrim lo posel and בית הלל Beit Hillel
says no like we've been saying, sleeping with a sister does not
make the wife forbidden. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosi, said רבי
יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, לא נחלקו בית שמאי ובית הלל בבועל אחות אשתו.
lo nechelku Beit Shammai u-Beit Hillel bevoel achot ishto. No, you're wrong.
Sister, everybody agrees, no impact. שלא פוסל את אשתו, she-lo posel et
ishto, his wife is not invalid, that's the פסוק pasuk of
אותה, otah, right ששכב אישה אותה, she-shachav ishah otah, אותה ולא שכבת
אחותה. otah velo shichvat achotah. So even בית שמאי Beit Shammai agrees
that sleeping with the sister does not forbid the wife to him.
במה נחלקו, Bamah nechlaku, what do they debate? בבועל חמותו, Bevoel chamoto,
the one possibility is you're right, the case of the mother. But
even that the wife's mother is only according to בית שמאי. Beit
Shammai. שבית שמאי אומרים פוסל ובית הלל אומרים לא פוסל. she-Beit Shammai
omrim posel u-Beit Hillel omrim lo posel. So basically everybody agrees that
it's more obvious to make in the case of mother than in
the case of sister, except here he's saying that when sister, everybody
agrees it's not a it doesn't make the wife forbidden, the only
issue is mother and there, even there, only בית שמאי Beit Shammai
says that sleeping with the mother makes the wife forbidden.
Now, וכולי vechulei ואתהן ve-es-hen thing we just interpreted.
Yeah well like we said before some other דרשה. drasha. Okay. So
במה נחלקו Bamah nechlaku fine. ובית הלל לא פוסל. u-Beit Hillel lo
posel. לפי שבתחילה הוא מותר בכל הנשים. Lefi she-vetchilah hu mutar bechol
hanashim. Now we're going to say the logic about why maybe the,
you know, the wife's sister might be forbidden. Okay. And this is
a nice logical pitch, it turns into some, you know, shows a
little comparison contrast between the wife and the husband. So let's take
a look. לפי שבתחילה Lefi she-vetchilah הוא מותר בכל הנשים שבעולם והיא
מותרת בכל האנשים שבעולם. hu mutar bechol hanashim shebaolam vehi muteret bechol
ha-anashim shebaolam. Before they got married, he could have married any woman,
she could have married any man. כנסה kensah he married her, הוא
אוסרה והיא אוסרתו. hu osrah vehi osartu. Once they get married, he
makes her forbidden to certain people and she makes him forbidden to
certain, well we're going to say that, and she makes him forbidden
to certain people. Of course it's very clear that her status is
the one that is mostly redefined. מרובה איסור שאסרה מאיסור שאסרתו. Merubeh
issur she-asrah me-issur she-asartu. It's great,
much greater is the prohibition that he creates on her than she
creates on him. שהוא אוסרה בכל האנשים שבעולם she-hu osrah bechol ha-anashim
shebaolam he makes her forbidden to absolutely every other man, now would
be an act of adultery, והיא לא אסרתו אלא בקרובותיה. vehi lo
asartu ela bikrovoteha. The only person she, only the only people she
proscribes him from are her relatives. Her mother, her sister, etc. Now,
so that's the reality, a clearly a lack of real parallel. והלא
דברים קל וחומר. Vehalo devarim kal vachomer. ומה הוא שאסרה בכל האנשים
שבעולם U-mah hu she-asrah bechol ha-anashim shebaolam he makes her forbidden in
all men, so in that case, שוגג באסור לה, shogeg be-asur lah,
if she actually sleeps with one of the men that she's forbidden
to, אינה נאסרת במותר לה eina ne-eseret be-mutar lah that doesn't affect
her status vis-a-vis the husband, if she was unintentional, if she unintentionally
committed adultery, it does not make her forbidden to her husband, even
though, all right, right, even yes, even though her obviously prohibition is
a much more, much wider, much more all-encompassing.
הוא שלא אסרתו אלא בקרובותיה hu she-lo asartu ela bikrovoteha when it
comes to his status, he's only been limited by her immediate relatives,
so that case, שוגג באסור לו, shogeg be-asur lo, if he unintentionally
slept with a woman he is forbidden with, his wife's sister, אינו
דין שלא נאסר לו במותר לו. eino din she-lo ne-esar lo be-mutar
lo. How much more so should that not affect his status vis-a-vis
his wife? Okay, so that's pretty makes right, that makes a lot
of sense, certainly talking about שוגג, shogeg, right, שוגג shogeg if, if
a woman who commits adultery בשוגג beshogeg isn't forbidden on her husband,
certainly a man who בשוגג beshogeg sleeps with his wife's sister won't
affect the status of his wife, right, because the idea that his
act could be more severe, you know, in terms than his wife's
act of adultery, it just makes no sense, his wife is the
one that is, you know, that her prohibitions are much more global.
Also, we could say the fact that she's אסור asur to everybody,
like you said, then shows that hers is the status that is
redefined, she is the one onto whom we put this status, מותר
אסור mutar assur and so on. Now... So her act is much
more likely to make her forbidden, right? Because she, her, again, it's
more global and we focus on her status. And if that's not
true in a case of שוגג, shogeg, how much more so is
his act, sleeping with a woman he's forbidden with, his sister, not
going to make him forbidden, not going to make him forbidden just
like that's in a case of שוגג. shogeg. There's no question that
it's not going to be more severe than adultery. But the question
is what about when it's במזיד? bemezid? And במזיד bemezid a case
of adultery, it will make her forbidden, maybe his act of sleeping
with a sister will have some parallel effect. Yeah, Dov.
I'm happy to understand this purely
formally, but like למעשה, lemayseh, how do you commit adultery בשוגג? beshogeg?
Well, you think the husband's dead.
Oh, that's the oh, so that's the underlying assumption.
That would be the cases we're talking about. I mean, could be
others, you think the guy is the husband, it's the middle of
the night or whatever, but yeah.
Okay, fine.
Or let's just say even בשוגג beshogeg certainly because like we were
saying before, the sister
prohibition outlives.
Yeah, but that's why there's a tiny הוה אמינא hava amina and
we need a פסוק. pasuk. But okay, but anyway, but certainly not
to say more חמור. chamur. The most קל וחומר kal vachomer you'd
have is equal. Okay, so anyway, so that's why it's certainly not
going to be worse. But how about
במזיד? bemezid? So וזו אדים לשוגג vezo adim leshogeg it's an interesting
language of this ברייתא. braita. That's good for שוגג shogeg that it's
not going to be worse. למזיד מנין? lamezid minayin? How about במזיד?
bemezid? Maybe at least the same way adultery makes her forbidden, maybe
sleeping with the sister creates a prohibition. תלמוד לומר אותה. Talmud lomar
otah.
So that was the הוה אמינא hava amina and the answer is
אותה. otah. אותה לשכיבתה אותה, otah lishchivat otah, when she sleeps with
another man, it makes her forbidden, ואין שכיבת אחות אוסרתה, vein shchivat
achot osartah, not when her sister sleeps with another man.
Is all a ברייתא? braita? All the way? Including this...
up to this line. Yep. Now we get to the Gemara. אמר
רבי אמי אמר ריש לקיש. Amar Rabbi Ami, amar Reish Lakish. So
said Rav Ami in the name of Reish Lakish, מאי טעמא דרבי
יהודה? mai ta'ama deRabbi Yehuda? What's the reason of Rabbi Yehuda that
says that according to Beit Hillel and Beit Shammai, sleeping with the
mother makes the wife forbidden? דכתיב... dechtiv... Wait a second, let me
go back... yeah.
Right. Well, no, this is according to, according to Rabbi Yehuda, even
Beit Hillel agrees. That's the one from before, right?
Are you confused by me?
Let's keep going. ואת האשה ואת אמה. ve'et ha'ishah ve'et imah. דכי
כל הבית כלו בשרפה? dechi kol habayit kulo bisreifah? What, you literally
burn the whole house? Meaning, nice image, but do you actually execute
the wife? What did the wife do? אם אינו עניין לשרפה, im
einu inyan lisreifah, if you're not going to execute the wife when
he slept with the mother, תנהו עניין לאיסורה, tenei inyan le'issura, at
least the act of sleeping with the mother affects both women and
even makes the wife forbidden. And that's, he's claiming everybody agrees, according
to the other opinion, it's only the position of Beit Shammai. According
to Rabbi Yose, it's only Beit Shammai who would say that. אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda, amar Shmuel, says Rav Yehuda
in the name of Shmuel, אין הלכה כרבי יהודה. ein halacha keRabbi
Yehuda. We don't rule like Rabbi Yehuda, so we do not rule
that a... that sleeping with the mother makes the woman... makes the
wife forbidden. That would only be a Beit Shammai position, not a
Beit Hillel, and we don't rule that way. ההוא דעבד איסורא בחמתיה.
Hahu de'avad issura bachamteh. A man basically had sex with his mother-in-law.
אתייה רב יהודה נגדיה. Atyei Rav Yehuda nagdeh. Rav Yehuda took him
and gave him lashes because this was after that they were no
longer executing. אמר ליה, Amar lei, yeah, אמר ליה, amar lei,
so Rav Yehuda said to him, אי לאו דאמר שמואל אין הלכה
כרבי יהודה, ee lav de'amar Shmuel ein halacha keRabbi Yehuda, if Shmuel
had not already ruled that we don't say like Rabbi Yehuda, אסרינא
לך איסור עולם, asrina lach issur olam, I would make you forbidden
for your wife forever. But we don't rule like Rabbi Yehuda, so
you can go back living with your wife, but you shouldn't have
been sleeping with your mother-in-law. Okay, moving on. מאי איסור קל? Mai
issur kal?
Now, this הוה אמינא hava amina that we said before, which I
told you referred to that called adultery an איסור קל, issur kal,
which is pretty shocking, that's going to be the conclusion of the
Gemara, but now the Gemara's going to get to it. When we
wanted to say that wife's sister should be an איסור חמור issur
chamur and we were comparing it to an איסור קל, issur kal,
what did we mean by an איסור קל? issur kal? So אמר
רב חסדא amar Rav Chisda מחזיר גרושתו משנישאת. machzir gerushato misheniset. A
man who remarries his divorced wife after she had married another man.
So what does that mean? What's the נאסר העושה? ne'esar ha'oseh? Here's
the case. בא להאי אסרה אהאי. Ba la-hai asra a-hai.
So if this one had sex with her, meaning, Reuben, forget Rachel
and Leah and the whole thing. Okay, Reuben is married to Rachel.
He divorces her. She goes over and she now marries Barak, stage
two. So now stage two she's married to Barak, okay.
So then in stage three, Barak divorces her and she goes and
she remarries Reuben. Now Reuben did a prohibition, he remarried his divorced
wife after she married somebody else. But you know who else, but
you know what else happened when he remarried her? Now, if even
if he were to divorce Rachel, Rachel would now be אסורה assura
to Barak, because she's also Barak's divorced wife who married, who married
Reuben, right?
So here's the case. So now he's gone ahead and married Reuben,
and then Reuben, right, Reuben divorced her. So now Barak is going
to sleep with his ex-wife who now is forbidden based on the
fact that she has remarried to Reuben. So מחזיר גרושתו משנישאת. machzir
gerushato misheniset. בא להאי אסרה אהאי. Ba la-hai asra a-hai. So if
this one had sex with her, meaning, when
Barak married her and had sex with her,
made her forbidden to Reuben. בא לאידך. ba la-idach.
Then came ahead Reuven and remarried her, אסרה להאי, asrah l'hai, made
her forbidden to Barak. So therefore, what is how are we reading
it? It's this is a case of so how does the line
read? במקום, Makom, it's not really בא, ba, it's really married. ומה
במקום שבא איסור קל, U'mah bemakom she'ba issur kal,
Reuven now has married, not just בא, ba, married Rachel who is
an איסור קל. issur kal. Why is she an איסור קל? issur
kal? Because it's מחזיר גרושתו, machzir grushato, it's a simple לאו. lav.
And what was the effect of בא איסור קל? ba issur kal?
נאסר האוסר. ne'esar ha'oseir.
Barak will now be forbidden to Rachel, and Barak was the one
that made Rachel forbidden to Reuven. All right, very complicated. Anyway, fine.
That act of marrying Rachel makes her אסורה asura to Barak. So,
and therefore, if that's true, how much more so sleeping with the
wife's sister. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute. מה למחזיר גרושתו
משניסת שכן נטמאה הגוף. Mah l'machzir grushato misheniseis sheken nitma'ah haguf.
One minute, you cannot compare this. And this is going to be
the question of any comparison to wife's sister. When something is done
with the wife herself and she becomes forbidden, that's because she did
something, it was something done with her herself. That is going to
change her status. So in this case, she herself married Reuven. That
will affect her status vis-a-vis Barak. Number one. Number two, ואיסורא ברוב.
ve'issura berov. It's a broader prohibition. Now, why exactly this is a
broader prohibition than wife's sister is not so clear. רש״י Rashi takes
out those words, תוספות Tosafot has a convoluted way of reading it.
We'll skip that for right now. ואיסורא איסור עולם. Ve'issura issur olam.
And number two or number three is, is that the is that
in this case, she's always going to be forbidden to Reuven and
then afterwards to Barak, as opposed to wife's sister which is only
as opposed to as opposed to wife's sister which is only while
the wife is alive. So this case is not קל, kal, it's
more חמור. chamur. Number one, because it's it's never going to this
status is always going to be there. And number two and most
importantly, because it's one thing to say the woman's status changes when
she did some act, but not when some act was done with
her sister. So what type of comparison is this? So אלא אמר
ריש לקיש, Ella amar Reish Lakish, יבמה. yevama. So a wife awaiting
you know בייבום. b'yibum. So יבמה למאן? yevama l'man? What happened with
this sister-in-law? אילימא לאחר, Ilima l'acher, so it was a wife awaiting
ייבום yibum and she had sex with another man. Okay, now how
is that going to make her forbidden? So וכדרב המנונא, uk'deRav Hamnuna,
we'll go like רב המנונא. Rav Hamnuna. דאמר רב המנונא, d'amar Rav
Hamnuna, שומרת יבם, shomeres yavam, a woman awaiting ייבום, yibum, שזינתה, she'zinta,
had sex with another man, אסורה ליבמה. asura l'yibama. She becomes forbidden
now to the brother-in-law. Okay, so and how here does it read?
It's an איסור קל, issur kal, a simple לאו, lav, don't sleep
you know לא תהיה אשת המת החוצה לאיש זר. lo tihyeh eishes
hamais hachutza l'ish zar. So that's איסור קל. issur kal. What's the
effect of this איסור קל? issur kal? That the brother-in-law who is
the אוסר, oseir, who made her forbidden, now becomes forbidden to him
when she sleeps with another man. Yeah, she's forbidden to him, right?
And now has to give her חליצה. chalitza. Okay, that's a pretty
good comparison. It was only a simple לאו lav and she becomes
forbidden to him. But again, the key difference is, yeah, because she
did something wrong, not her sister. That's always going to be the
key difference.
Okay, one minute. מה ליבמה שכן נטמאה הגוף. Mah l'yevama shekein nitma'ah
haguf. She went ahead and her her own person was involved in
the violation. ואיסורא ברוב. Ve'issura berov. Number two, as opposed to wife's
sister where it only like affects this one man, here she's forbidden
to the whole world. Number three, okay, so therefore there's no comparison.
אלא ליבמה לאחים. Ella l'yevama l'achim. So it's a case where she
becomes one brother did something with his sister-in-law and now she becomes
forbidden to the other brothers. What's the case? דעבד בה מאמר האי.
D'avad bah ma'amar hai. Let's say one brother did מאמר, ma'amar, remember
מאמר? ma'amar? אסרה להאי. Asrah l'hai. So now made her forbidden to
the other brothers to do ייבום. yibum. If another brother didn't pay
attention to that and went and did ייבום yibum anyway, בא לאידך,
Ba l'idach, had sex with her, אסרה להאי. asra l'hai. That makes
her obviously forbidden to the first brother who did מאמר. ma'amar. Okay,
so that's an איסור קל issur kal violating the rabbinic problem of
of מאמר ma'amar and makes her forbidden on the other brother. One
minute. מאי אריא דבא לה שני? Mai arya d'ba lah sheini? It
has nothing to do with the fact that the second brother had
sex with her that makes her forbidden. אפילו עבד בה נמי מאמר,
Afilu avad bah nami ma'amar, as long even if the second brother
did מאמר, ma'amar, that now gets to you know make the first
brother out of the picture or now they're both you know sort
of have their hands tied. Gemara says no. הא לא קשיא כרבן
גמליאל. Ha lo kashya k'Rabban Gamliel. No, that's like רבן גמליאל. Rabban
Gamliel. דאמר, d'amar, there's a little חזרה chazara to see if you
remember any of this, אין מאמר אחר מאמר. ein ma'amar achar ma'amar.
A מאמר ma'amar following a מאמר ma'amar has no meaning, so if
the second brother did מאמר, ma'amar, the first brother would would status
would not be compromised. אלא, Ella, okay, fine, fine, forget מאמר. ma'amar.
אפילו נתן לה גט ואפילו חלץ. Afilu nasan lah get v'afilu chalatz.
If the second brother did something however different than the first brother,
gave her a גט get or gave חליצה, chalitza, that would similarly
make her forbidden to the first brother. Okay, so it's not an
issue. Yes, the first brother the second brother did something wrong. He
shouldn't have done something once the first brother did מאמר. ma'amar. And
if he does something wrong now, it'll make her forbidden to the
first brother. But it's not an act of sex makes her forbidden
to the first brother. Any act in the world of ייבום, yibum,
חליצה, chalitza, גט, get, etc., will now make her forbidden to the
first brother. And I don't want to get back into this if
you don't remember these things from whatever. אלא אמר רבי יוחנן, Ela
amar Rabi Yochanan, it was a quick חזרה Chazara to see how
much you remembered from a month ago. אלא אמר רבי יוחנן, Ela
amar Rabi Yochanan, says רבי יוחנן, Rabi Yochanan, סוטה. Sotah. So we're
talking about a suspected adulteress. So סוטה למאי? Sotah le-mai? Who is
suspected adulteress to who? אילימא לבעל? Ilima le-baal?
So basically
means the following: בא על הבעל אסר לה לבועל. Ba al ha-baal
asar lah le-boel.
So meaning who is now making, who is she sleeping with and
who is she forbidden to? So rather than thinking the obvious thing,
she committed adultery, she's forbidden to her husband, then it's basically just
a case of adultery, right? That's too easy. We'll get to them
in a minute. So we're saying, no, no, no, here's the problem.
A woman commits adultery, you know who else she's אסור assur to,
not only her husband? Who else is the woman אסור assur to,
in addition to her husband? The man she did it with. The
adulterer. Okay. So now she committed adultery, she's forbidden to the adulterer.
Now, if her husband has sex with her, she's now, that act
is going to make her forbidden to the adulterer. Wait one minute.
Her husband having sex with her makes her forbidden to the adulterer?
She's forbidden to the adulterer anyway, right? So בא על הבעל אסר
לה לבועל. Ba al ha-baal asar lah le-boel. מאי
איריא בא על הבעל? Mai irya ba al ha-baal? Now that the
husband has sex with her, she's forbidden to the adulterer? אפילו נתנה
גט, Afilu natna get, אפילו אמרה איני משקה. afilu amra eini mashka.
As soon as she has sex with the other man, even if
now they get divorced, she's forbidden to the adulterer. So that's not
the איסור קל issur kal we're talking about, the prohibition of a
woman with the man she committed adultery. אלא סוטה לבועל. Ela Sotah
le-boel. Okay, her prohibition to, the fact that she's prohibited to sleep
with a man other than her husband. Okay, the basic prohibition of
adultery. That's the איסור קל. issur kal. So the גמרא Gemara says,
that's the איסור קל? issur kal? This is what we're now ending
at now what I told you way before, that we're calling adultery
an איסור קל, issur kal, okay, that she can't have sex with
a man other than her husband, and if so it makes her
forbidden to her husband. So the גמרא Gemara says wonderful. That's not
סוטה. Sotah. האי איסור קל הוא? איסור חמור הוא, דהיינו אשת איש.
Hai issur kal hu? Issur chamur hu, dehainu eshet ish. What do
you mean that's a light prohibition? That's one of the biggest prohibitions.
It's adultery, it's חיובי מיתה. chiyuvey mita. Okay, how can you call
that, how could you call that a light prohibition? אלא אמר רבא,
Ela amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, 22 says אלא ela because we
really are saying exactly what we were just saying a minute, but
now we're at least owning it. We're not trying to say it
like a סוטה Sotah thing. אלא אמר רבא אשת איש. Ela amar
Rava eshet ish. Yeah, you're right. We are talking about adultery and
then we're saying an act of adultery makes her forbidden, which is
an איסור קל, issur kal, then an act of sleeping with the
sister should make her also forbidden, which is an איסור חמור. issur
chamur. So what's קל kal and חמור chamur here? So וכן כי
אתא רבין אמר רבי יוחנן אשת איש. Vekhein ki ata Ravin amar
Rabi Yochanan eshet ish. ומאי קרי ליה איסור קל? U-mai karei leh
issur kal? Why are we calling it a light prohibition? שאינה אוסרה
אוסרה כל ימיו She-eina ossra ossra kol yamav because it's different than
wife's sister because here she could get divorced. So again, it's a
very, it's a very weird argument that this is a lighter prohibition
than the prohibition of sister. But that is what we're using to
create the הוה אמינא hava amina that sleeping with the sister makes
the woman forbidden and we need the פסוק pasuk to tell me
not that way. One minute. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, it
says so in a תוספתא. Tosefta. אבא חנן אומר משום אבא אלעזר
אשת איש. Abba Chanan omer mishum Abba Elazar eshet ish. ומה במקום
הבעל איסור קל, U-ma bimkom ha-baal issur kal, שאינה אוסרה אוסרה כל
ימיו, she-eina ossra ossra kol yamav, נאסר העושה. ne'essar ha-osseh. If a
man has sex with a married woman, which is an איסור קל
issur kal because she's not, she won't necessarily always be forbidden to
him, nevertheless makes her forbidden to the husband who, who is the
one that affected her status. הבא על איסור חמור, Ha-ba al issur
chamur, somebody who comes on a weightier prohibition, wife's sister, which will
always be אסור, assur, this man sleeping with the wife's sister, שאוסרה
אוסרה כל ימיו, she-ossra ossra kol yamav, אינו דין שנאסרה העושה? eino
din she-ne'essra ha-osseh?
How much more should the one who affected her status, the wife,
become forbidden? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar אותה. otah. אותה שכיבתה פוסלתה. Otah
shchivatah poseltah. No, only when she commits, does the forbidden act of
sex can she become forbidden. ואין שכיבת אחותה פוסלתה. Ve-ein shchivat achotah
poseltah. Not something her sister has done. Now תוספות Tosafot of course
points out that even if we're going to call adultery איסור קל,
issur kal, it doesn't answer the basic point the גמרא Gemara has
already recognized, which is the woman didn't do anything. So what's the
הוה אמינא hava amina that she should be forbidden? If you look
at תוספות Tosafot אלא, Ela, two lines down into it towards the
end of the line. אבל קצת קשיא. Aval kzat kashya. He only
says קצת קשיא. kzat kashya. I don't know why קצת. kzat. But
he says אבל קצת קשיא, aval kzat kashya, he says, לרי, le-Ri,
דאכתי תקשי ליה כל הני פירכי דלעיל. de-achti tiksheh leh kol hani
pirchei de-la'eil. Even if you're willing to call this an איסור קל,
issur kal, what about all the questions we asked earlier?
דקתני נטמא הגוף ואיסורא דרוב. De-katni nitma ha-guf ve-issura de-rov. So even
forget איסורא דרוב issura de-rov and whatever that means, נטמא הגוף, nitma
ha-guf, right? That's the whole basic point. Of
course if a woman commits adultery, that impacts her status. What type
of a הוה אמינא hava amina is it that something her sister
will do would impact her status? And that we really don't even
have a good הוה אמינא. hava amina. But anyway, at least it's
not the הלכה halacha in the end. So you had a question?
I would say, to me the flaw in the logic is yeah
he could divorce her at any time. Yeah. But she could also
die any second. You don't know.
Yeah, but one is in her mind—exactly, exactly, exactly. All right.
Hold on, just trying to get something going here. Okay, fine, I'll
know somehow. All right, let's continue now. All right, so we at
least have that was our הוה אמינא, hava amina, but in the
end, wife's sister does not—A does not make her forbidden, the act
of sleeping, which should have been a more obvious thing.
I don't know this thing this weird, could you close that blind,
I'm getting weird shadows going on here.
Anyway, does not make her forbidden and B, and B,
oh that's much better, thank you. Okay, and B, the more logical,
the more logical possibility that there would be a semblance of a
marriage and that would make him forbidden to go back to his
wife, that we don't say either. Okay, now we get this cryptic
statement of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose in the משנה, Mishnah, right? Which
is רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says, here's the line of רבי יוסי:
Rabbi Yose: כל שפוסל על ידי אחרים פוסל על ידי עצמו. Kol
sheposel al yedei acherim posel al yedei atzmo. Anybody who invalidates, you
know, vis-à-vis others, invalidates oneself. וכל שאינו פוסל על ידי אחרים אינו
פוסל על ידי עצמו. V'chol she'eino posel al yedei acherim eino posel
al yedei atzmo. If you don't invalidate others, you don't invalidate yourself.
What the heck does that mean? So let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, מאי קאמר רבי יוסי? Mai ka'amar Rabbi Yose?
What's he saying? אילימא דקאמר תנא קמא, Ilima d'ka'amar Tanna Kamma, now
we're going to get back to the case that we read into
the משנה, Mishnah, which there's no necessary basis for reading it into
the משנה, Mishnah, other than as תוספות Tosafot points out, because maybe
we think that this is the case that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
was responding to. So this is the case we said yesterday. So
אילימא דקאמר תנא קמא דאזיל איהו וגיסו למדינת הים. Ilima d'ka'amar Tanna
Kamma d'azil ihu v'giso l'medinat hayam.
So this is the case where, this is the case we did
yesterday, that here, his brother-in-law,
right, Barak, I need more colors, who's married to
Leah, okay, so what happens? His wife, wait, one second here, the
ones that are left behind. His wife and his brother-in-law, they go
למדינת הים. l'medinat hayam. Okay, they're
business partners. They go למדינת הים. l'medinat hayam. Okay, so that's the
case. And then they hear that they both died. So what happens?
They both died, the fact that she's no longer married, and that
his wife is dead, allows him now to marry Leah. They hear
that they both died. Then it turns out that they were both
alive. So what is going to be Leah's story? Leah heard that
her husband died, she married Reuven, okay, and now it turns out
her husband's alive. What's Leah's story? She's אסורה asura to everyone, right?
אסורה מזה ומזה, asura mizeh umizeh, all the negative consequences. What's Rachel's
story? Rachel's story is, well, Reuven married the sister, turns out that
he wasn't allowed to marry the sister, he can go back to
Rachel. That's what you're saying. So there's a lack of a parallel,
because if you look at Leah married enough to Reuven to give
her all of the negative consequences, then if she's married enough to
Reuven, then she should be his quasi-wife and he should be אסור
asur to go back to Rachel. But no, we're going to look
at this as this is a case of a woman who had
a report of her husband's death and it was false and she
suffers the negative consequences. This is a case of a man who
heard of his wife's death and married
the sister and he doesn't have to suffer the negative consequences. So
there's a lack of consistency.
So that maybe is the case of the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma,
and that maybe רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is responding to and saying
you've got to be consistent. So let's take a look. So אילימא
דקאמר תנא קמא דאזל איהו וגיסו למדינת הים, Ilima d'ka'amar Tanna Kamma
d'azal ihu v'giso l'medinat hayam, his wife and brother-in-law went to a
faraway country and then finds out that, you know, they got married,
he and Leah, and then finds out that they were both alive.
אשת גיסו אסורה, Eshet giso asura, his brother-in-law's wife, Leah, is forbidden
now to go back to her husband, ואשתו שרייה, v'ishto sharya, but
his wife Rachel is permissible to him. That, and we have this
lack of parallel, וקאמר ליה רבי יוסי, v'ka'amar lei Rabbi Yose, and
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says to the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, כי
היכי דאשתו שרייה, ki heichi d'ishto sharya,
now which way is he going to take consistent, which way are
you going to go, קולא או חומרא? kula o chumra? So let's
say he's saying לקולא. l'kula. כי היכי דאשתו שרייה, Ki heichi d'ishto
sharya, if you're going to say that he wasn't seen as married
to Leah and therefore he's allowed to go back to Rachel, so
if he wasn't seen as married to Leah, אשת גיסו נמי שרייה,
eshet giso nami sharya, let Leah go back to her husband, okay?
So that's what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is saying לקולא. l'kula. אי
הכי, Ei hachi, if that's true, he shouldn't have said the words
כל שאינו פוסל על ידי אחרים אינו פוסל על ידי עצמו. kol
she'eino posel al yedei acherim eino posel al yedei atzmo. Anybody that's
not invalidated vis-à-vis others shouldn't be invalidated to him. That's not the
way the argument goes, it's the reverse. כל שאינו פוסל על ידי
עצמו, Kol she'eino posel al yedei atzmo, if it's not invalidated to
him, if Rachel isn't going to be אסורה asura to him and
therefore אינו פוסל על ידי אחרים, eino posel al yedei acherim, then
therefore Leah shouldn't be אסורה asura to others, Leah shouldn't be אסורה
asura to her husband. Right, we if we're going to say it
לקולא, l'kula, we start with the case that's מותר. mutar. If Rachel's
going to be מותרת, muteret, if he's going to go back to
him, then Leah should be מותרת muteret to go back to her
husband.
So מיבעי ליה, mibai lei, it should have said it. אלא, Ela,
okay, so maybe he's saying it לחומרא. l'chumra. כי היכי דאשת גיסו
אסורה, Ki heichi d'eshet giso asura, the same way Leah's forbidden to
her husband, אשתו נמי אסורה. ishto nami asura. So Rachel should be
forbidden to him. So that would mean כל שפוסל הא תינח, kol
she'poseil ha teinach, so that's good for the first part of the
sentence. כל שפוסל, kol she'poseil,
if anybody that is invalidated by others, also is invalidated to him.
So Leah who's invalidated to her husband creates an invalidity of Rachel
to him. That works when it's saying it creates an איסור. issur.
But כל שאין פוסל מה עבידתיה, kol she'ein poseil mai avidetih, what
do you do with the second half of his statement? When it
doesn't... it's not vis-a-vis others, it's not vis-a-vis him. Like what case
is that that you need that to say? Okay. So but we're
close, we're close to an answer. So אמר רב אמי, Amar Rav
Ami, רישא. reisha. We're going to introduce this second part of his
statement by introducing... we're going to deal with the second part of
the statement by introducing another scenario. What's the other scenario? Something we
taught much earlier in the פרק. perek. ניסת על פי בית דין
תצא ופטורה מן הקרבן, Nisset al pi beis din tetzei u'peturah min
ha'korban, when she does it by בית דין's beis din ruling, she
has to get divorced and she's exempt from a קרבן. korban. על
פי עדים תצא וחייבת בקרבן. Al pi eidim tetzei v'chayaves b'korban.
With witnesses meaning על פי עד אחד, al pi eid echad, with
witnesses however she goes out and she... and she brings a קרבן.
korban. יפה כוחה של בית דין שפוטר מן הקרבן. Yafeh kochah shel
beis din she'poteir min ha'korban. And בית דין beis din is better
that it exempts her from a קרבן. korban. It's funny that it
quotes this part of the משנה mishna because this is all about
the קרבן. korban. But what he really means to introduce is what
we know all along, the difference of עד אחד eid echad and
עדים, eidim, okay, what the גמרא's Gemara been assuming. That all of
the negative consequences are only by עד אחד, eid echad, not by
עדים. eidim. Everybody remembers that, I assume, right? Okay. So now he's
going to... so now here's how we're going to set it up.
וקאמר תנא קמא, V'ka'amar tanna kamma, the תנא קמא tanna kamma says:
לא שנא על פי עדים, lo shena al pi eidim, it doesn't
matter if the remarriage happened based on two witnesses, in that case,
even if they turn out alive, everybody can go back and be
happy. דאשת גיסו שריא. d'eishes giso sharya.
In that case, right, the wife... his brother-in-law's wife can go back.
ולא שנא על פי בית דין, v'lo shena al pi beis din,
and it doesn't matter if it's done based on בית דין, beis
din, which means one witness, דאשת גיסו אסירא. d'eishes giso asira. So
meaning, this case that witnesses come back, can Leah go back to
Barak? Well, if they had married based on two witnesses, the answer
is yes. If they had married based on one witness, the answer
is no. So the תנא קמא tanna kamma says whether it's two
witnesses or one witness, whether Leah can go back to Barak because
it was two witnesses or whether she can't go back to Barak
because it was one witness, either way Reuven can go back to
Rachel. Okay, that's the תנא קמא. tanna kamma. There's not a parallel.
Leah sometimes can go back to Barak, sometimes not depending on one
versus two witnesses. Reuven can always go back to Rachel.
He minimizes the discrepancy.
No minimize, it's just another scenario where
right there won't be a discrepancy. Right. Exactly. That... okay, but so
that's a case of two witnesses. So they're saying either whatever happens
to Leah, Rachel can go back. That's what תנא קמא tanna kamma
is saying. אוקיי, וקאמר ליה רבי יוסי. Okay, v'ka'amar lei Rabbi Yosi.
Now רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says back: לא, על פי בית דין
דפוסל על ידי אחרים פוסל על ידי עצמו. no, al pi beis
din d'poseil al yedei acherim poseil al yedei atzmo. When it was
בית דין, beis din, meaning one witness, and Leah is now forbidden
to her husband, Rachel's forbidden to her husband. על פי עדים דאינו
פוסל על ידי אחרים. Al pi eidim d'eino poseil al yedei acherim.
If
it was two witnesses where Leah is not forbidden to her husband,
אינו פוסל על ידי עצמו, eino poseil al yedei atzmo, then Rachel
isn't forbidden to her husband. Not a bad reading, right? Basically he's
saying you can't split the הלכה. halacha. If... if Leah's... it's forbidden
to her husband, Rachel will also be forbidden to him. If there
are scenarios where Leah isn't forbidden to her husband, like it was
על פי עדים, al pi eidim, not על פי עד אחד, al
pi eid echad, then Rachel also won't be. Okay, but that's a
very basic point. You cannot go ahead and say that this marriage
is significant enough to make her forbidden to Barak without making her
Rachel also forbidden to him. Yes.
So the whole reason why we were מיקל meikel for עד אחד
eid echad was this whole משום עיגונא הקלו בה רבנן, mishum iguna
hikilu bah rabanan, right? But are we going to do the same
thing for him? In other words, if one עד eid came back
and said oh,
Rachel is dead, then he'll marry Leah, but you know, he's never
going to be an עגון agun because he can always just marry
somebody else.
Right. So that's a very good question in terms of
what testimony he needs in order to go ahead and marry... and
marry another woman. So there's an earlier תוספות, Tosafot, let me see
if I don't remember where it is precisely, let me find it
in one minute.
So you're right, it just basically sounds like it was one עד.
eid. Of course,
it could be one עד eid that Barak died and two עדים
eidim that Rachel died. So it could still work. But anyway, let
me just see if I can quickly find that. That's a very
good question. One minute.
Yeah, if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, Michael asked an
excellent question which we didn't discuss, which is how many witnesses does
he need to know that his wife died before he can marry
Leah? Can he also rely on one witness? Right? Do I understand
the question? Normally we only rely on one witness because of עגונה.
agunah. So look quick back at תוספות דף צ"ד עמוד ב, Tosafot
daf tzadi dalet amud beis, the first תוספות אף על גב. Tosafot
af al gav. Where he says like this.
Three lines down in the narrow lines. Everybody see where I am
here? Yeah, on דף צ"ד עמוד ב. daf tzadi dalet amud beis.
He says, yeah. He says no yeah אלא הכא Ela Hacha is
the second line. Three lines down ומהי דאמרו לו שני עדים שמת
אשתו ועד אחד על גיטו Umai De'amru Lo Shenei Eidim Shemeis Ishto
Ve'eid Echad Al Gito או בעד אחד על מיתת אשתו אין יכול
לישא אחותה. O Ve'eid Echad Al Misas Ishto Ein Yachol Lisha Achoso.
Okay and then he goes on. Alright so the גמרא's Gemara point
is correct that for him to be able to remarry to marry
Leah he would need two witnesses. We don't rely on one witness
that his wife died. That's not a special case that we should
rely on one witness. Let him marry some other woman in the
world other than Leah okay? So this is a case where we're
having that both of them went away and there's various testimony. It
would always be that there were two witnesses about he about her.
The question is was there one or two witnesses about Barak in
terms of Leah's remarriage? So that's an excellent point. Okay רבי יצחק
נפחא אמר Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha Amar back to the גמרא. Gemara. רבי
יצחק נפחא Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha says לעולם הסיפא Le'olam Hasifa that we're
not going to the case back to a case of two witnesses
to introduce a case where Leah is not forbidden. But here's the
scenario where even with one witness Leah is not forbidden. Anybody remember
a case where a woman's husband is reported dead she remarries turns
out he's alive and she's not forbidden even though it was only
one witness? Sort of a pop quiz. Where she let's
say
well it would be where
well actually it's not a fair question because well okay. One case
is that she didn't really do נישואין nisu'in with the second guy
right? She only did קידושין kiddushin with the second guy. But actually
I'm a little confusing you because the גמרא Gemara actually has it
about well let's take a look. הדא אזל ארוסתו וגיסו Hada Azal
Arusaso Vegiso הדא
אזל אשתו וגיסו. Hada Azal Ishto Vegiso. So it is a קידושין
kiddushin case but not the case I just said I'm sorry I
confused you. The case question here is what is Rachel's relationship to
Reuven? Is Rachel נישואין nisu'in or is Rachel קידושין? kiddushin? Now why
does that matter right? It matters for the following reason. Remember the
question is that he's going to go ahead and he's going to
do a קידושין kiddushin with Leah. And the question about what that
would do to is this seen as a quasi-marriage when it turns
out that his wife is alive? Why is he allowed to go
back to his wife? Why do we say it looks like they're
married and this becomes a type of a אחות גרושתו achos grushaso
or something? Why doesn't she require a גט? get? So the reason
is because once his wife shows up alive everybody says well he
couldn't have been married to Leah the sister was alive and he
was married to the sister right? Ah but if there's only קידושין
kiddushin with Rachel we discussed this before people might say maybe that
marriage never got finished. You know it's not a תנאי tenai it
never got finished maybe he really was married to Leah. So in
the case where there was only קידושין kiddushin right then it's more
reasonable to think that this would be problematic and it would require
a גט get and would make him אסור assur to go back
to Rachel. So let's take a look. Okay הדא אזל ארוסתו וגיסתו
Hada Azal Arusaso Vegissoso one case is his ארוסה arusa went with
his brother-in-law והדא אזל אשתו וגיסו. Vehada Azal Ishto Vegiso. Okay וקאמר
תנא קמא Vekamar Tana Kamma and the תנא קמא Tana Kamma says
לא שנא אשתו וגיסו Lo Shena Ishto Vegiso I don't care about
the case of full wife where certainly Rachel's not going to be
forbidden because nobody's going to look at Rachel like a nobody's going
to look at the other marriage like it was like it was
binding ולא שנא ארוסתו וגיסו Velo Shena Arusaso Vegiso and I don't
care if Rachel was only his ארוסה arusa and maybe it has
a more of a semblance of him being married to Leah. Either
way אשת גיסו אסירה Eshes Giso Asira Leah can't go back to
her husband ואשתו שרי Ve'ishto Shari he can go back to Rachel.
Whether the case looks more or less like he was married to
Leah because of whether Rachel was an ארוסה arusa or not either
way he can always go back to Rachel. וקאמר ליה רבי יוסי
Vekamar Leh Rabbi Yossi and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says back to
him אשתו וגיסו Ishto Vegiso when he was fully married to Rachel
דאיכא למימר תנאי הוה ליה בנישואין De'ika Lemeimar Tenai Hava Leh Benisu'in
nobody will think that there was a condition in the נישואין nisu'in
and therefore clearly he was married to Rachel and therefore the marriage
to Leah does not look like a marriage in hindsight דאינו פוסל
על ידי אחרים אינו פוסל על ידי עצמו. De'eino Posel Al Yedei
Acherim Eino Posel Al Yedei Atzmo. So that case he goes so
far to say look you know what I'm going to say now
we're going to have רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi לקולא Lekula not לחומרא.
Lechumra. If he is really married to Rachel נישואין nisu'in therefore this
does not look like a marriage at all. If this doesn't look
like a marriage at all guess what? Not only can he go
back to Rachel you know what else? Leah can go back to
Barak. Once it turns out that Rachel was alive and that then
everybody will know and this was a real נישואין nisu'in nobody questions
this marriage everybody will know this wasn't a marriage. What was it?
It was a mistake. But nobody will have thought it was a
marriage.
Not even זנות. zenus.
Well it might have been זנות zenus but בשוגג. beshogaig. Everybody will
know it's not a marriage. Therefore Leah can even go back to
Barak in that case. Now רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is being
מיקל. meikil. Okay ארוסתו וגיסתו Arusaso Vegissoso however what I will disagree
with is the case of ארוסה arusa דאיכא למימר תנאי הוה ליה
בקידושין De'ika Lemeimar Tenai Hava Leh Bekiddushin people might think that the
marriage with Rachel never worked out ופוסל על ידי אחרים Veposel Al
Yedei Acherim and in that case then Leah will be forbidden to
her husband אף פוסל על ידי עצמו Af Posel Al Yedei Atzmo
then she can't even go back so this is. So this is
a much more I think interesting read of רב יוסף. Rav Yosef.
רב יוסף Rav Yosef is consistent. We're not going to split the
פסק psak but we might go both ways לקולא, le-kula, we might
go both ways לחומרא, le-chumra, okay? So and here he's introducing a
new factor. If this was a נשואין, nisuin, then you know what,
in hindsight, caused their sisters, not in a normal case of a
woman whose husband is reported dead, but in this case caused their
sisters and nobody questions this marriage, when it turns up that they're
alive, everybody will look in hindsight at this and say, oh, they
were never married. And since they'll look at it like this, not
only can he go back to רחל, Rachel, she can go back
to ברק, Barak, because it has no semblance of a marriage. So
there he's going to be מקיל mekil both ways. However, if this
was only an אירוסין, eirusin, and people would continue to look at
this as that that looked like a marriage, but in the same
way she's forbidden to ברק, Barak, he's forbidden to רחל. Rachel. So
רב יוסף Rav Yosef not only is saying we have to be
consistent, he's actually even introducing a case where because it's a special
case of sister, where they can go back to their husband.
Didn't he do the same thing with the
woman, like it was a mistake, you know? No, because then she
could have gotten a גט. get. When he turns out that she
married another man, it always looks, if there's no sister involved, it
always looks like it was a real marriage because the second guy,
because people will think her husband divorced her, right? But here, since
רחל Rachel is alive, it was impossible for him to have been
married to לאה. Leah.
In the first case, it's really treated like a מקח טעות.
mekach taut. Again, it's not a מקח טעות, mekach taut, it's about
how people are perceiving it, but okay, yes, people realize that it
was a טעות. taut. That is correct. Okay. Okay. אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, so says רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, הלכה כרבי יוסי. halacha k'Rabbi
Yossi. We rule like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. Okay. Now, which רבי
יוסי? Rabbi Yossi? All right, so let's take a look. מתיב רב
יוסף, Metiv Rav Yosef, ומי אמר שמואל הכי, u-mi amar Shmuel hachi,
did שמואל Shmuel really say that? דאיתמר, d'itmar, you know what, we're
going to end right there because I have to actually leave a
little earlier today.
So we will we will continue to unpack this tomorrow.